# 江西 南昌
Jiangxi, Nanchang
# 滕王阁
Tengwang Pavillion
# 雪鱼现在在南昌
I am in Nanchang right now
# 来了之后才发现江西人有多能吃辣
I found out how much spicy Jiangxi people can handle after arriving here
# 在这边她们把辣椒做成饼
Here, they make chilis into a cake
# 当零食吃
And eat it as a snack
# 待会我就是去买一点辣椒饼
I am going to buy some chili cakes in a moment
# 体验一下辣椒饼的威力
to experience the power of the chili cakes
# 阿姨推着车 拿着辣椒饼来了
She’s coming with the cart of chili cakes
# 不用帮忙吗
May I help you?
# 不用 不用
No, thanks!
# 我想给帮忙抬过去的
I wanted to help her carrying those
# 不用的 这点东西还用帮忙啊
No, thanks! It is a piece of cake.
# 一天就准备一车 加两书包的饼啊
You prepared one cart plus two bags of cakes for just one day?
# 啊哈哈 我就是带着 也卖不了这么多
Hahaha I just prepared them, can’t sell them all
# 能卖多少就卖多少
I sell as much as possible
# 我多带一点 怕有顾客多要的话
I prepared more in case any customer wants more
# 我没法回家拿了 就多带一点
I can’t go home to refill, so I prepared extra with me
# 一天卖不完的 再好的生意我都没卖完过
Can’t sell them all. I never sold out even on a very good day
# 阿姨 我们是第一次见这个辣椒饼
It’s our first time seeing the chili cakes
# 这些袋子里都是吗
Are these all chili cakes in the bags?
# 都是 有10多种
Yes, more then ten flavors
# 你没有见过辣椒饼吗
You have never seen a chili cake before?
# 没有啊
Never
# 你是外地的哇
You are not local!
# 对呀
Yeah
# 如果你是南昌人 你就见过了
If you are local, you would have seen them
# 南昌人就喜欢吃这个东西 把这个当零食吃
Nanchang people really like to eat them as snacks
# 我们小的时候就在学校门口买着吃
We bought and ate them by the school gates when we were little
# 还有比我年纪大的也在学校门口买着吃
People older than me also bought them there
# 阿姨 辣椒饼有几种口味的啊
How many flavors of the chili cakes are there?
# 有奶味的 草莓味的 山楂味的
I have milk flavor, strawberry flavor, Chinese hawthorn flavor...
# 辣椒饼还分为各种水果味的
Chili cakes with different fruit flavors
# 这是我第一次听到
I have never heard of that before
# 卖的最好的是哪一种啊
Which one sells the best?
# 这两种吗 它们有什么样的区别啊
These two? What’s the difference between them?
# 可是我感觉不出来有什么样的不同 颜色吗
I can’t feel any difference, maybe color?
# 这个辣 这个微辣
These ones are spicy, these ones are mildly spicy
# 从颜色上看 这个辣一点的颜色会鲜艳一点
Looking at the colors, the spicy ones are brighter
# 哇 这个是南瓜干
Wow it’s pumpkin cake
# 是用糯米粉做的南瓜干
Pumpkin cake are made out of rice flour
# 这个辣椒饼啊就是我们南昌人吃
Only us Nanchang people eat these chili cakes
# 别的地方的人吃不惯的
People elsewhere can’t get used to the taste
# 你尝尝看
Try it
# 真的可以尝吗
Really?
# 可以的 随便
Sure, help yourself!
# 哪个是不辣一点的 给我一个小的吧
Which ones are less spicy? May I have a smaller piece?
# 来给你
Here you go
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 这是面粉做的 不辣一点的 入口没有什么辣味
It’s made of flavor. Less spicy ones. Can’t tastes much spiciness with a bite
# 像吃小零食一样的感觉
It’s like eating a snack
# 吃掉一片辣椒饼的时候 感觉到很辣
After finishing the whole chili cake, I feel the spiciness
# 这个是什么呀
What are these
# 这个是奶味的辣椒饼
These are milk flavored chili cakes
# 这个是刚吃的南瓜干 这个是高辣度的饼
These are the pumpkin cakes I just ate, these are very spicy chili cakes
# 阿姨这个是什么呀 看起来像巧克力
What are these? They look like chocolate
# 那是甜酱辣椒饼
Theses are sweet chili cakes
# 这一桌就是各种各样的辣椒饼啊
All kinds of chili cakes here
# 我们这边南昌的女孩子要吃辣一点的
If the Nanchang girls prefer spicier ones,
# 我就给她做辣一点的了
I will make them more spicy chili cakes.
# 要吃微辣的就做微辣的 还有咸辣的
If you want mild spicy, there are mild spicy ones; I also have salty and spicy ones.
# 这里还有一份特辣的
Here are extra spicy chili cakes
# 我可能就能吃一般辣的
I probably can only handle normal spicy ones
# 一般辣的你都吃不了 你只能吃这样的
You can’t handle normal spicy ones, you can handle these
# 啊 我连一般辣的都吃不了
Ah, I can’t even handle normal spicy ones
# 就是只能吃甜辣的了
So just sweet chili cakes
# 因为你怕辣嘛
Because you are afraid of spiciness
# 阿姨 我称一点吗 好吧
Could you weigh some of these for me, please?
# 这几种辣椒饼价格都一样吗
Is the price of different kinds of chili cakes the same?
# 全部是一样的
All the same
# 那就混着称吧
Then mix some together
# 多少钱一斤啊 阿姨
How much per jin (per 0.5 kg)
# 4块钱一两 40元一斤
4 Yuan per liang (per 50 g), 40 Yuan per jin (per 0.5 kg)
# 可以的 这几种辣椒饼混着称吧
Ok, mix these kinds of chili cakes together
# 我多尝一尝味道 体验南昌人吃辣的感觉
I want to try more flavors, to experience how Nanchang people eat the spicy snacks
# 哈哈 南昌人是很能吃辣椒
Haha, Nanchang people can handle the spiciness very well
# 都要把辣椒做成饼来吃
They made chilis into cakes
# 还要当成零食来吃
and eat them as snacks
# 我听人说吃完饭没事 就看电视时候吃辣椒饼
I heard that people here eat chili cakes while watching TV after a meal
# 半斤辣椒饼一会就吃完了
Half a jin (250 g) of chili cakes are gone very fast
# 你吃不惯就随便装一点 就不要给钱了
If you can’t get used to the taste, just pack a few and I won’t charge you
# 我给你夹几筷子 你品尝一下
Let me give you a few to taste
# 不不不
No no
# 没事没事 都是我自己做的
It’s fine, I made them all by myself
# 不不 稍微称一点特色的
No no, just weigh some signature ones
# 这些辣椒饼都是特色
All these chili cakes are special
# 我担心太辣吃不动
I’m afraid they are too spicy for me
# 我也不想挣那么多钱
I don’t care about earning that much money
# 因为这个需要晚上做出来
Because they have to be made overnight
# 如果生意太好的话 我就做不出来了
If they are all sold out, I can’t make more chili cakes fast enough
# 我就没有时间睡觉了 我会累坏的
Then I won’t have time to sleep, I would be exhausted
# 这是怕生意太好啊
You are afraid that the business becomes too good
# 阿姨 您是从早上10点开始摆摊到下午7点吗
So you business is open from 10 AM to 7 PM?
# 是的
Yes
# 就一直在这个地方吗 是的
Here at this spot all the time? -Yes
# 中午我老公会送饭来
My husband sends me lunch at noon
# 我要走的时候她说忘了拿牌子
She said she forgot to put up the signs when we were about to leave
# 帮忙照看一下摊子
We looked after the business for a while
# 我的老顾客真的很多 我微信上就有3000多人
I have a lot of returning customers. I have about 3000 customers just on my WeChat
# 从1996年做到现在 365天每天都在这里
Since 1996, my business is always here, 365 days a year.
# 辣椒饼呢 简单来说就是辣椒加面粉做成的
Chili cakes are made out of chilis and flour
# 看像这种的 方块的 吃起来就会硬很多
Cubic ones like these have a harder texture
# 而片状的 就会软很多
Sliced ones are much softer
# 它的辣度是分口味和等级的
The spiciness is classified by different flavors and levels
# 有干辣的 甜辣的 还有奶油味的
We have a dry spicy flavor, sweet-spicy, and cream flavor
# 反正就是各种各样的辣度
All kinds of spiciness
# 不管是哪种辣椒饼
No matter which kind of chili cakes,
# 吃的时候感觉不到辣
you won’t feel the spiciness while eating
# 但是一整块吃下去就会觉得非常辣
But after eating a whole piece, you will feel very spicy
# 我刚才就仅仅尝了一口
With only a small bite back there,
# 我就感觉我的嗓子在冒烟
I already felt that my throat was on fire
# 可以想象到江西人吃辣的能力啊
You can imagine how much spiciness Jiangxi People can handle.